Guide to the Houston Folklore and Music Society records, 1951-2016 MS 668
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Houston Folklore and Music Society records
1967-2016
1951-2016
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Houston Folklore and Music Society
MS 668
2 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
These records mainly consist of news clippings and newsletters of the Houston Folklore and Music Society.
Biographical / Historical
Started in June 1951 by John Avery Lomax, Jr., Ed Badeaux, Howie Porper, Chester Bower, and Harold Belikoff, the Houston Folklore Society held their early meetings at the Jewish Community Center, the Downtown YMCA, and Hermann Park Pavilion. These meetings consisted of song swaps, folk dancing, and folk song concerts in conjunction with the Jewish Community Center. Early on, they also sponsored concerts by Pete Seeger, Doc Watson, and Lester Flatt and Earl Scruggs and the Foggy Mountain Boys.
In April 1988, the society changed its name to the Houston Folklore and Folk Music Society. The group began using a shortened version of that name, the Houston Folklore and Music Society on a consistent basis in 1990, though the shortened name had been officially incorporated by July 1988.
By June 1966, the society began publishing a newsletter that contained event information and articles about folk music. By 1968, the newsletter changed its name from the "Houston Folklore Bulletin" to the "Cotton Patch Rag."
Over the years, the society also began formalizing their events. During the 1980s, they held monthly pickin' parties, which still continue. In 1980, they started hosting concerts, which turned into Second Saturday Concerts at the West University Community Center. These have continued to this day with a variety of national and regional folk musicians performing. Moreover, they hold meetings on the first Monday of the month at the Jewish Community Center, where the group handles business matters and runs a song circle.
For more information about the society, please visit their website: houstonfolkmusic.org.
Content Description
These records contain news clippings, fliers, and newsletters, "The Houston Folklore Bulletin" and "The Cotton Patch Rag."
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Conditions Governing Access
This material is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Paul Cooper on behalf of the Houston Folklore and Music Society board in October 2016.
Accruals
Additional materails are expected for this collection.
Index Terms
Subjects
Music; Folk music -- Texas -- Houston; Social life and customs
Document Types
Folk music
Subjects (Corporations)
Houston Folklore and Music Society
- Series I: General, 1951-1993
  - Fliers, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - John A. Lomax, Jr. Memorial Concert (3 CDs), 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Lomax Benefactors Fund, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1951-1993 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: Newsletters, 1966-2016
  - List of missing newsletters, ca. 2000 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1967 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1976 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1985 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1986 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - 1988 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 1990 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 1991 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - 1992 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 1993 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 1999 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - 2000 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 2002 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 2003 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 2005 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 2006 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 2007 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 2008 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 2009 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 2010 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 2011 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 2012 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 2013 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 2014 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 2015 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 2016 (Box 2, Folder 23)